New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Predecessor Companies Collection
© 2006 University of Connecticut
New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Predecessor Company Collection.
undated, 1815-1907.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center.
New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad.
.5 linear feet.
MSS19910136
The collection holds documents related to early southern New England railroads, particularly those that were predecessor lines of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, including the Boston, Hartford and Erie Railroad; the Boston and New York Airline Railroad; the Central New England Railway; the Charles River Railroad; the Chicago and Evanston Railroad; the Connecticut River Railroad; the Hartford and New Haven Railroad; the Hartford, Providence and Fishkill Railroad; the Housatonic Railroad; the Housantonic and Naugatuck Railroad; the Meriden and Cromwell Railroad; the Meriden, Waterbury, and Connecticut River Railroad; the Naugatuck Railroad; the New Haven and Derby Railroad; the New Haven and Northern Railroad; the New Haven and Northampton Company; the New York and New England Railroad; the New York and New Haven Railroad; the New York, Providence and Boston Railroad; the Newburgh, Dutchess and Connecticut Railroad; the Norfolk County Railroad; the Philadelphia, Reading, and New England Railroad; and the Poughkeepsie and Eastern Railway. The collection also includes correspondence Julius Wadsworth, who operated a New York based bond brokerage that heavily invested in railroads and Charles F. Pond, president of the Hartford and New Haven Railroad.
History
The collection holds documents related to early southern New England railroads, particularly those that were predecessor lines of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, the railroad predominant railroad in the region from 1872, when it was established through the merger of the New York and New Haven Railroad and the Hartford and New Haven Railroad, to 1969, when it was absorbed into Penn Central.
Scope and Content
This collection contains journal entries, bills of lading, vouchers, receipts, invoices, and correspondence of several southern New England railroads. The topics document general railroad concerns, including locomotive and freight car parts and repairs, per diem costs on cars and rails, and bridge building.
Arrangement
Series I: Materials related to Julius Wadsworth, ( 1826-1886 ), contains documents, mostly correspondence related to Julius Wadsworth, who operated a New York based bond brokerage that heavily invested in railroads. The correspondence is primarly about railroads and financing.
Series II: Predecessor Companies ( 1815-1907 ) focuses almost exclusively on railroads that merged, at various times, into the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad. The collection holds documents related to the following railroads: Boston, Hartford and Erie Railroad; Boston and New York Airline Railroad; Central New England Railway; Charles River Railroad; Chicago and Evanston Railroad; Connecticut River Railroad; Hartford and New Haven Railroad; Hartford, Providence, and Fishkill Railroad; Housatonic Railroad; Housantonic and Naugatuck Railroad; Meriden and Cromwell Railroad; Meriden, Waterbury, and Connecticut River Railroad; Naugatuck Railroad; New Haven and Derby Railroad; New Haven and Northern Railroad; New Haven and Northampton Company; New York and New England Railroad; New York and New Haven Railroad; New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad; New York, Providence and Boston Railroad; Newburgh, Dutchess and Connecticut Railroad; Norfolk County Railroad; Philadelphia, Reading, and New England Railroad; Poughkeepsie and Eastern Railway. Documents related to Charles F. Pond can be found in the Hartford and New Haven Railroad folders.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to southern New England railroads. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
Central New England Railway; Charles River Railroad; Chicago and Evanston Railroad; Connecticut River Railroad; Hartford and New Haven Railroad; Hartford, Providence, and Fishkill Railroad; Housatonic Railroad; Housantonic and Naugatuck Railroad; Meriden and Cromwell Railroad; Meriden, Waterbury, and Connecticut River Railroad; Naugatuck Railroad; New Haven and Derby Railroad; New Haven and Northern Railroad; New Haven and Northampton Company; New York and New England Railroad; New York and New Haven Railroad; New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad; New York, Providence and Boston Railroad; Newburgh, Dutchess and Connecticut Railroad; Norfolk County Railroad; Philadelphia, Reading, and New England Railroad; Poughkeepsie and Eastern Railway
Subjects:
Railroads -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection contains donated and purchased materials acquired between 1990 and the present.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Materials related to Julius Wadsworth, 1826-1886
  - Correspondence from Julius Wadsworth, 1866-1885 (Other 1, Folder :1)
  - Correspondence to Julius Wadsworth, 1841-1886 (Other 1, Folder :2)
  - Other documents, 1826-1881 (Other 1, Folder :3)
- Series II: Predecessor Companies, 1815-1907
  - Boston and New York Airline Railroad, 1878 (Other 1, Folder :4)
  - Boston, Hartford, and Erie Railroad, 1864-1871 (Other 1, Folder :5)
  - Central New England Railway, 1899 (Other 1, Folder :6)
  - Charles River Railroad, 1847-1880 (Other 1, Folder :7)
  - Chicago and Evanston Railroad, 1885 (Other 1, Folder :8)
  - Connecticut River Railroad, 1850 (Other 1, Folder :9)
  - Hartford and New Haven Railroad, 1836-1856 (Other 1, Folder :10-11)
  - Hartford, Providence, and Fishkill Railroad, 1849-1877 (Other 1, Folder :12-13)
  - Housatonic Railroad, 1839-1862 (Other 1, Folder :14)
  - Housatonic Railroad and Naugatuck Railroad, 1850-1862 (Other 1, Folder :15)
  - Meriden and Cromwell Railroad, 1884-1886 (Other 1, Folder :16)
  - Meriden, Waterbury, and Connecticut River Railroad, 1887-1890 (Other 1, Folder :17)
  - Naugatuck Railroad, 1854-1861 (Other 1, Folder :18)
  - Naugatuck Railroad, 1849-1880 (Other 1, Folder :19)
  - Naugatuck Railroad, 1849-1887 (Other 1, Folder :20)
  - New Haven and Derby Railroad, 1853-1888 (Other 1, Folder :21)
  - New Haven and Northern Railroad, 1856 (Other 1, Folder :22)
  - New Haven and Northampton Company, 1870 (Other 1, Folder :33)
  - New York and New England Railroad, 1881-1895 (Other 1, Folder :23)
  - New York and New Haven Railroad, 1850-1864 (Other 1, Folder :24)
  - New York, New Haven, and Hartford Railroad, 1873-1907 (Other 1, Folder :25)
  - New York, Providence, and Boston Railroad, 1850-1853 (Other 1, Folder :26)
  - Newburgh, Dutchess, and Connecticut Railroad, 1879-1898 (Other 1, Folder :27)
  - Norfolk County Railroad, 1844-1853 (Other 1, Folder :28)
  - Philadelphia, Reading, and New England Railroad, 1897 (Other 1, Folder :29)
  - Philadelphia, Reading, and New England Railroad, 1894-1898 (Other 1, Folder :30)
  - Poughkeepsie and Eastern Railway, 1896-1906 (Other 1, Folder :31)
  - Other documents (unidentified railroads), undated, 1815-1887 (Other 1, Folder :32)